Miguel A. Sabogal García

Curriculum Vitæ

Mail: msabogal@est.uniatlantico.edu.co Web page: msabogal.github.io Telephone: + 57 3017958948

Over the last 3 years I actively participated in many physics research that resulted in international scientific publications. These experiences allowed me to acquire strengths in leadership, creativity, and perseverance while building skills in a wide range of programming languages, developing specialized software, and performing data management.

Research Experience, Publications, and Projects

Peer-Reviewed Publications

- Cardona, W., & Sabogal, M. A. Holographic energy density, dark energy sound speed, and tensions in cosmological parameters: H0 and S8. Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics, 2023(02), 045. D0I 10.1088/1475-7516/2023/02/045 arXiv:2210.13335.
- Oliveros, A., **Sabogal, M.A.,** & Acero, M.A. Barrow holographic dark energy with Granda–Oliveros cutoff. Eur. Phys. J. Plus 137, 783 (2022). DOI: 10.1140/epjp/s13360-022-02994-z.
- Sabogal, M. A., Parra, I. C., Bandera, M., Gallardo, J., & Mejía-Cortés, C. (2020, May). Mobility of localized beams in non-homogeneous photonic lattices. In Journal of Physics: Conference Series (Vol. 1547, No. 1, p. 012023). IOP Publishing. DOI: 10.1088/1742-6596/1547/1/012023.

In Preparation

 Sabogal, M.A., & Gonzalez, J.(2022). Hubble constant estimation from BAO signals with LSST-simulated data. <u>Draft</u>: zenodo.7131390.

Professional experience

02/2023 - Current **High school teacher**, Fundación Educativa Instituto Experimental del Atlántico "José Celestino Mutis". Tasks performed:

- Teaching Physics and programming courses
- Preparation of syllabus and pedagogical materials
- Examination preparation and student grading

05/2022 - 08/2022 **Research intern**, Red de Estudiantes de Astronomía de Colombia, and LSST observatory.

Tasks performed:

- Design and development of specialized software in Python and Writing of scientific articles
- Statistical analysis using Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC)
- Non-parametric reconstruction using Gaussian Processes (Machine Learning)
- Develop the end-to-end project plans with the execution team

06/2020 - 12/2022 Junior Software Developer, Instituto Colombiano de Neurociencias Aplicadas SAS.

Tasks performed:

- Assisting Senior Developer with the development, and maintenance of all menu maintenance portal code using Python
- Developing automation scripts in Python for data management
- Keeping the project manager informed of the overall status of the solution
- Be part of technical discussions and solution

Volunteer experience

08/2019 - 06/2022 Supportive Mentor, Physics Program, Universidad del Atlántico

Tasks performed:

- In-person and virtual classes of Physics and Mathematics
- Academic support to students in their first semesters and mid-career.
- Mentoring colleagues providing advice and guidance on best practice and development techniques

Education

• 2015 – 2022 **Physicist,** Bachelor's degree/ *Universidad del Atlántico*.

Computational skills

Specialized software Cosmic Linear Anisotropy Solving System (CLASS) and Gaussian processes (GaPP): Advanced

Python: Advanced, C/C++: Intermediate, Fortran 90: Intermediate, MATLAB/Mathematica/Excel: Advanced, HTML: Basic

Techniques: Process Automation, Machine Learning, Statistical analysis using MCMC, Web scraping, Object-oriented programming.

Tools: Selenium, Beautifulsoup, Scrapy, NumPy, SciPy, Pandas.

Honors and Awards

- Funding award "Enabling Science Program 2021 Award 51", granted by the Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST) observatory.
- Undergraduate Honors Thesis, Universidad del Atlántico.

Additional languages

English (TOEFL certified)Read: C1Speak: B2Write: B2Listen: C1Test date: Nov 2022PortugueseRead: A2Speak: A2Write: A1Listen: A2

Presentations and Events

Event: XIV Latin American Symposium on High Energy Physics

Type of event: International Congress

Type of participation: Speaker

Conference title: <u>Decoding Holographic Dark Energy in the structure formation.</u>

Place: QUITO, ECUADOR - Universidad San Francisco de Quito, 14/11/2022 - 18/11/2022.

Event: CoCo 2021: Cosmology in Colombia

Type of event: National Congress

Type of participation: Speaker

Conference title: Cosmological analysis of Barrow holographic dark energy model considering the Granda-Oliveros

infrared cutoff.

Place: Online. 08/09/2021 - 11/09/2021.

Event: RECA Internships 2022 Symposium

Type of event: National Symposium

Type of participation: Speaker and Research intern

Conference title: <u>Hubble constant estimation from BAO signals with LSST-simulated data</u>.

Place: Online - Universidad de Antioquia, 29/08/2022 - 30/08/2022.

Courses and certifications

PYTHON IN ASTRONOMY Astropy Course(2022)

Work references

Mario A. Acero Ortega, Ph.D. in Physics ORCID.

Associate Professor, Physics Program, Faculty of Basic Sciences, Universidad del Atlántico.

Regular Member and Co-Founder of Colombian Network on High Energy Physics

Distinction from Neutrino Physics Center, Fermilab: Batavia, Illinois, US

Contact info: marioacero@mail.uniatlantico.edu.co or (+57) 313 497-3415